# Alireza Vahid, PhD

Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering University of Colorado Denver alireza.vahid@ucdenver.edu www.alirezavahid.com

#### Who I am

Wireless architectures and protocols have become too complicated to scale and meet the ever-increasing demands of future applications such as the Internet of Things, vehicular systems, mmWave and THz communications, WiFi6, 5G, 6G and beyond. It is time for a fundamental change in our approach. I jointly develop communication algorithms and antenna structures to harness the computational power of the analog forefront, and drastically improve network throughput, power consumption, and latency. Beyond communications, I collaborate with experts to develop new models and codes to overcome the challenges of emerging data storage technologies such as Racetrack and DNA archival storage. I seek to impact wireless networking, sensing, and data storage through my innovations.

#### Research Interests

- Theory of Wireless Networking with Programmable Computational Antennas
- Network Information Theory, Communication Theory, and Signal Processing
- Coding Theory and its Applications in Data Storage and High-Performance Computing

#### Education

Cornell University

Ithaca, NY

MSc & PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

2015

- PhD Thesis: The Impact of Imperfect Feedback on the Capacity of Wireless Networks
- 2015 Cornell Best PhD Thesis Award
- Advisor: Salman Avestimehr, PhD

### Sharif University of Technology

BSc in Electrical Engineering

Tehran, Iran 2009

### **Positions Held**

University of Colorado Denver	Denver, CO
• Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering	2017 to present
Theia Technologies Founder and CEO	Denver, CO 2020 to present
• Duke University Adjunct Assistant Professor of Electrical & Computer Engineering	Durham, NC 2018
• Duke University • Postdoctoral Research Scientist	Durham, NC 2014-2017
• Qualcomm Inc. Innovation Fellow	San Diego, CA 2013
• Bell Labs • Research Intern	Holmdel, NJ 2012

## **Funding**

Funding Agency	Year	Role	Total	Share	Title
			Budget		
NSF	2020	PI	\$500k	50%	Cross-Layer Interference Management: Bringing Interfer-
					ence Alignment to Reality
Lab Venture Partners	2019	PI	\$125k	100%	Theia: A Low-Complexity Distributed Interference Man-
					agement Solution
State of Colorado	2019	PI	\$90k	100%	Opportunistic Communication Protocols in Dynamic
					Wireless Systems
University of Colorado	2018	PI	\$30k	100%	Deceptive Solutions in Data Transmission
Qualcomm Inc.	2013	PI	\$100k	50%	Collaborative Interference Management

### **Selected Awards & Honors**

• Best Paper Award at IEEE CCWC	2020
• Lab Venture Challenge Award for my invention "Theia" (\$125k)	2019
• Runner-up Best Paper Award at Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN)	2019
• New Faculty Research Award, CU Denver (\$30k)	2019
• Creative Research Collaborative (CRC) Fellowship, CU Denver	2018
• Young Upwardly Mobile Professor (YUMP) Award, CU Denver	2018, 2019
• Best PhD Thesis Award, School of ECE, Cornell University	2015
• Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship (\$100k)	2013
• Best PhD Teaching Award, School of ECE, Cornell University	2011
• Jacobs Scholar Fellowship, School of ECE, Cornell University	2009
• Ranked 2nd among over 360,000 in Iranian University Entrance Exam	2004
• Ranked 2nd in Azad University National Entrance Exam	2004
• Silver Medal in Iranian National Physics Olympiad	2003

### **Journal Publications**

- (J1) T. Levy, A. Vahid, R. Giryes, "Ranking Recovery from Limited Comparisons using Low-Rank Matrix Completion," to appear in the journal of Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, 2020.
- (J2) S. Nassirpour, A. Vahid, "Embedded Codes for Reassembling Non-Overlapping Random DNA Fragments," *IEEE Transactions on Molecular, Biological, and Multi-Scale Communications*, 2020.
- (J3) M. Johnny, A. Vahid, "Exploiting Coherence Time Variations for Opportunistic Blind Interference Alignment," *IEEE Transactions on Communication Theory*, 2020.
- (J4) A. Vahid, "On the Degrees-of-Freedom of Two-Unicast Wireless Networks with Delayed CSIT," *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 65, no. 8, pp. 5176–5188, 2019.
- (J5) A. Vahid, A. R. Calderbank, "Throughput Region of Spatially Correlated Interference Packet Networks," *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 65, no. 2, pp. 1220–1235, 2019.

- (J6) G. Mappouras, A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, D. Sorin, "Extending Flash Lifetime in Embedded Processors by Expanding Analog Choice," *IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design Integrated Circuits and Systems*, vol. 37, no. 11, pp. 2462–2473, 2018.
- (J7) A. Vahid, V. Aggarwal, S. Avestimehr, A. Sabharwal, "Interference Management with Mismatched Partial Channel State Information," EURASIP Journal on Wireless Communications and Networking, 2017.
- (J8) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, S. Avestimehr, and Y. Zhu, "Binary Fading Interference Channel with No CSIT," *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 63, no. 6, pp. 3565–3578, 2017.
- (J9) A. Vahid, A. R. Calderbank, "Two-User Erasure Interference Channels with Local Delayed CSIT," *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 62, no. 9, pp. 4910–4923, 2016.
- (J10) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Approximate Capacity Region of the MISO Broadcast Channels With Delayed CSIT," *IEEE Transactions on Communications*, vol. 64, no. 7, pp. 2913–2924, 2016.
- (J11) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Capacity Results for Binary Fading Interference Channels with Delayed CSIT," *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 60, no. 10, pp. 6093–6130, 2014.
- (J12) A. Vahid, C. Suh, and S. Avestimehr, "Interference Channels with Rate-Limited Feedback," *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 58, no. 5, pp. 2788–2812, 2012.

### **Conference Publications**

- (C1) M. A. Farahani, A. Vahid, A. E. Goodwell, "Evaluating Ecohydrological Model Sensitivity to Forcing Variability with an Information Theory-Based Approach," *Proceedings of American Geophysical Union (AGU* Fall Meeting), 2020. **Interdisciplinary work in environmental engineering.**
- (C2) I. Shomorony A. Vahid, "Communicating over the Torn-Paper Channel," to appear in IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM), 2020.
- (C3) S. C. Lin, I. H. Wang, A. Vahid, "Capacity of Erasure Broadcast Channels with Single-User Delayed CSI and Common Messages," to appear in IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM), 2020.
- (C4) M. Johnny, A. Vahid, "Embedding Information in Radiation Pattern Fluctuations," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, 2020.
- (C5) S. Nassirpour, A. Vahid, "Throughput, Delay, and Complexity Tradeoffs in Interference Channels," *Proceedings of 10th IEEE Annual Computing and Communication Workshop and Conference (CCWC)*, 2020. Winner Best Paper Award.
- (C6) A. Vahid, I. H. Wang, S. C. Lin, "Capacity results for erasure broadcast channels with intermittent feedback," Proceedings of IEEE Information Theory Workshop (ITW), 2019.
- (C7) Mappouras, A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, D. Sorin, "GreenFlag: Protecting 3D-Racetrack Memory from Shift Errors," *Proceedings of 49th Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN)*. Runner-up Best Paper Award.
- (C8) S. C. Lin, I. H. Wang, A. Vahid, "No Feedback, No Problem: Capacity of Erasure Broadcast Channels with Single-User Delayed CSI," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory* (ISIT), 2019.

- (C9) A. Vahid, "Finite Field X-Channels with Delayed CSIT and Common Messages," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, 2018.
- (C10) A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, "ARQ for interference packet networks," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, 2018.
- (C11) G. Mappouras, A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, D. R. Hower, D. Sorin, "Jenga: Efficient Fault Tolerance for Stacked DRAM," *Proceedings of IEEE International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD)*, 2017.
- (C12) A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, "When does spatial correlation add value to delayed channel state information?" Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT), 2016.
- (C13) G. Mappouras, A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, D. Sorin, "Methuselah Flash: Rewriting Codes for Extra-Long Storage Lifetime," Proceedings of 46th Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN), 2016.
- (C14) A. Eslami, A. Velasco, A. Vahid, G. Mappouras, R. Calderbank, D. Sorin, "Writing without Disturb on Phase Change Memories by Integrating Coding and Layout Design," *Proceedings of Memory Systems (MEMSYS)*, 2015.
- (C15) A. Vahid, I. Shomorony, R. Calderbank, "Informational Bottlenecks in Two-Unicast Wireless Networks with Delayed CSIT," Proceedings of Allerton conference, 2015.
- (C16) A. Vahid, R. Calderbank, "Impact of Local Delayed CSIT on the Capacity Region of the Two-User Interference Channel," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, 2015.
- (C17) A. Vahid, G. Mappouras, A. Velasco, R. Calderbank, and D. J. Sorin, "Virtual Cells and Concatenated Codes for Flash Memory," *Proceedings of Fifth Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (NVMW)*.
- (C18) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Binary Fading Interference Channel with No CSIT," Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT), 2014.
- (C19) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Communication Through Collisions: Opportunistic Utilization of Past Receptions," *Proceedings of IEEE Infocom*, 2014.
- (C20) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Approximate Capacity of the Two-User MISO Broadcast Channel with Delayed CSIT," *Proceedings of Allerton conference*, 2013.
- (C21) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Binary Fading Interference Channel with Delayed Feedback," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, 2012.
- (C22) A. Vahid, M. Maddah-Ali, and S. Avestimehr, "Interference Channel with Binary Fading: Effect of Delayed Network State Information," *Proceedings of Allerton conference*, 2011.
- (C23) A. Vahid, V. Aggarwal, S. Avestimehr, and A. Sabharwal, "On the Capacity of Multi-hop Wireless Networks with Partial Network Knowledge," Proceedings of Allerton conference, 2010.
- (C24) A. Vahid and S. Avestimehr, "The Two-User Deterministic Interference Channel with Rate-Limited Feedback," *Proceedings of International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, 2010.

## **Preprints and Submitted Papers**

(P1) I. Shomorony, A. Vahid, "Torn-Paper Coding," submitted to IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 2020.

- (P2) S. Nassirpour, A. Vahid, "On Duality of Stability and Capacity Regions in Interference Networks," submitted to IEEE Transactions on Communications, 2020.
- (P3) A. Vahid, S. C. Lin, I. H. Wang, "Erasure Broadcast Channels with Intermittent Feedback," submitted to IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 2020.
- (P4) S. C. Lin, I. H. Wang, A. Vahid, "Capacity of Two-User Erasure Broadcast Channels with Single-User Delayed CSI," submitted to IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 2020.
- (P5) M. Johnny, A. Vahid, "Distributed Blind Interference Management with Computational Antennas," submitted to IEEE Transactions on Communications, 2020.
- (P6) H. Jafarian, I. Shomorony, A. Vahid, "Design and Development of Deceptive and Agile Wireless Infrastructures against Adversarial Traffic Analysis Attacks," under review.

### **Patents**

- (Patent1) A. Vahid, "Embedding Information in Radiation Pattern Fluctuations," US Provisional Patent, 2020.
- (Patent2) A. Vahid, "Low-Complexity Practical Implementation of Blind Interference Alignment using Reconfigurable Antennas," US Provisional Patent, 2019.
- (Patent3) D. Sorin, G. Mappouras, R. Calderbank, A. Vahid, "Systems and Methods for Improving Memory Bandwidth," US Provisional Patent, 2019.

#### **Graduate Students**

• Sajjad Nassirpour

PhD Candidate

MSc Candidate

- Started 2019. Best Paper Award at CCWC'20. One accepted journal paper.
- Yalda Nael
  - Female candidate working on Erasure Broadcast Channels
- John McFarlane MSc Candidate
  - Working on data security and deceptive communications

## **Teaching Experience and Student Mentorship**

• Instructor, University of Colorado Denver

- Data and Information Inference Theory (G)

Fall 2019

- Engineering Probability and Statistics (UG)

Spring 2019

- Random Processes (G)

Fall 2018

- Digital Communication Systems (G)

Spring 2018 & 2019

- Information and Coding Theory (G)

Fall 2017 & 2019

Data+ Summer Program, Duke University

Mentor for Water Reservoir Project

Durham, NC Jun. to Aug. 2015

- Advised a team of undergraduates and two graduate students

- Aligned the capabilities of the undergraduates with the demands of the external client
- Managed communication with the external client
- Conducted comprehensive study of water reservoirs across North America
- Quantified the role of human operator in water level fluctuations

## Teaching Assistant, Cornell University

Ithaca, NY Fall 2010

Random Signals in Communication and Signal Processing

- 2011 Cornell University Best PhD Teaching Award

### **Professional Activities**

• TPC member,

- IEEE Annual Computing and Communication Workshop and Conference (CCWC)	2020
- Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (NVMW)	2021
- IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)	2021

- Reviewer:
  - IEEE Transactions on Information Theory
  - IEEE Transactions on Communications
  - IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications
  - IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology
  - IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory
  - IEEE INFOCOM
  - IEEE GLOBECOM
  - IEEE Information Theory Workshop
  - IEEE Communication Letters
  - IEEE Magnetic Letters
- Panel Reviewer:
  - National Science Foundation, CISE (CCF and CNS), ENG (CCSS)
- Organized the North American School of Information Theory

2016

• Chair of student travel award committee, IEEE ISIT

2020

### **Professional Activities**

- IEEE Senior Member
- IEEE Communication Society Member
- IEEE Information Theory Society Member
- IEEE Young Professionals Member